<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gospel liberty sent down from heaven in a suffering time, or, Christian toleration given and granted by the Lord, about the worship of God ... by R.F.</title>
            <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40932</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F484</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24320</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08121743</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08121743</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40909</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40932)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40909)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1229:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gospel liberty sent down from heaven in a suffering time, or, Christian toleration given and granted by the Lord, about the worship of God ... by R.F.</title>
                  <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Freedom of religion.</term>
               <term>God --  Worship and love.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40909:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GOSPEL LIBERTY Sent down from Heaven in a ſuffering Time.</p>
            <p>OR Chriſtian Tolleration given and granted by the Lord, about the Worſhip of God, and in matters of Faith and Salvation, to the people of God, and primitive Chriſtians, which is matter of comfort to them that are acquainted with God in the Spirit, and have the Teſtimony of his Love, and the ſignification of his acceptation who are true and faithful to God, In the principles and practices of the Saints in Chriſt Jeſus: and primitive Chriſtians, according to the perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of God upon their hearts and conſciences, though for ſo doing they be attended with a ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring condition, which aforetime was and now is annexed to believing.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Philip. 1.29.</hi>
               </bibl> For unto you it is given in the behalf of Christ not only to believe on him, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tim. 3.12.</hi>
               </bibl> Yea and all that will live godly in Christ Jeſus, ſhall ſuffer perſecution.</q>
            <p>Written the 14th of the 3d moneth 1664. By R. F.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:40909:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40909:2"/>
            <p>FOr aſmuch as God who is abſolute in himſelf, who hath juriſdiction over all fleſh and ſpirits, principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and powers, thrones and dominions, created,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.16.17. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.26.27.</note> ordained, and eſtabliſhed by him, and for him, doth give, grant, and allow of a liberty to men and Chriſtians, as men and Chriſtians. Firſt, as men in the creation to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the end for which they were created: and Secondly, as Chriſtians in communion and covenant with him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.31.</note> being children of the free woman, and are commanded and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by the Lord as a people in covenant with him, to ſtand faſt in the liberty (of their tender conſciences to God-ward, in point of Religion and worſhip of God) wherewith Chriſt hath made them free, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1. They ought not to be denyed or hindred of that liberty which is given, granted, and allowed unto them, by the Lord as men (to hinder them for anſwering the end of their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation) neither ought the true Chriſtians and people in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God, to be denyed of liberty of Conſcience, in point of Religion and worſhip of God, but to have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of conſcience in matters of Faith and Salvation given, granted, and allowed unto them:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.13.14,</note> Becauſe they are thereunto called of God, and it is againſt the doctrine of the Apoſtles, contrary to the minde and will of the Lord, and in oppoſition to the Scriptures, and the practice of the primitive Chriſtians, to deny and refuſe to grant it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe the Saints and true Chriſtians are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Lord to ſtand faſt in the liberty (of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience allowed in the goſpel) wherewith Chriſt hath made them free. Secondly, becauſe they are forbidden to be intangled again with the yoke of bondage (in point of religion and worſhip of God) as by the Scripture is evident. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:40909:3"/>To deny liberty of conſcience in point of Religion and worſhip of God to any perſons or people,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.24.25.26.27.28.29.30.31. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.23.24.</note> is to deny that right which is given and granted unto them by the Lord, for Religion and worſhip, is that wherein Gods honour and glory is concerned: and as it is God who is to be worſhiped, ſo the worſhip is the worſhip of God, wherein conſcience is concerned, and not the worſhip of man, and it belongs to the Lord to preſcribe, declare, reveal or make known his own worſhip both in matter and manner, and after made known to the conſcience or a capacity in man, conſcience ought to ſtand free, and not be forced threfrom, that God may perſwade it to own, allow of, and cloſe in with the ſame, and every man ought to be fully perſwaded in his own heart, as by the Scripture is evident and plain, and who hath the like right, power, wiſdome, and skil to inform, reform and perſwade the heart of a man to him who made it, and knowes beſt the frame, temper, and diſpoſition of it, and hath abſolute power to puniſh it, or be merciful unto it, as it is diſobedient or obedient to him in diſcipline, worſhip and government: for the right of heart ſearching and trying doth properly belong to the Lord, and not unto man as by the Scripture is plain.</p>
            <p>Therefore God ought to have his own right preſerved and kept unviolated, that he may inform, reform, and perſwade the heart and conſcience of man, both to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the end for which he was created, and to fear, reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, honour, and obey him in conſcience to God-ward, as a worſhipper of him, and the right of men ought to be preſerved, that they may not be forced from but left to their liberty, to receive and retain the trueth and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of God, in matters of Faith and Salvation, that they
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40909:3"/>may continue therein, and not be perſwaded or forced therefrom by any man, for the Apoſtle declares to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> that they did run well, but ſome hindred them, that they ſhould not obey the truth, and they that hindred them did not well in ſo doing: for ſaith he this perſwaſion cometh not of him that calleth you, as by the Scripture is plain. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.7.8.</p>
            <p>They who are againſt liberty of conſcience in matters of Faith and Salvation, and would either by perſwaſions or threatnings hinder people from obeying and walking in the truth of the Goſpel, which God makes known un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and perſwades them to walk in, do not well in ſo doing, and though he that was born after the fleſh did perſecute him that was born after the ſpirit, he did it without any right or authority from God, and therefore the ſon of the bond woman muſt be caſt out, and not be heir with the ſon of the free woman, as ſaith the Scripture. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29.30.</p>
            <p>Chriſt hath purchaſed a liberty,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1.</note> and fredome for the Saints and believers in him in point of religion, and in matters of faith and ſalvation, and therefore they ought not to be deprived of it: but ought to have it granted and allowed unto them, by ſuch as are profeſſors of him, that as they have begun in the ſpirit,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1.2, 3.</note> they may not be forced and carried back again into the fleſh. But may have the liberty of their conſciences in matters of Faith and Salvation allowed and granted, to obey the truth of the goſpel according to the manifeſtation and perſwaſion of the word and ſpirit of God, and that they may run well in the way of the Lord without moleſtation or hindrance by them that profeſſe the truth. <hi>For in Jeſus Chriſt neither Circumciſion availeth any thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.7.8.</note> 
               <hi>nor uncircumciſion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40909:4"/>but a new Creature, and Faith which worketh by love</hi> Gal. 5.5.6. Gal. 6.15.16.</p>
            <p>And as many as walk according to this rule, that is to ſay the rule of the new creature,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.1.2.3.4.5.6.7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.15.16,</note> 
               <hi>which is the ſpirit of Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Gal. 4.6. Peace be on them and mercy, and upon the Iſrael of God. <hi>For as many as are led by the Spirit of God, they are the Sons of God.</hi> Rom. 8.14.</p>
            <p>So many and no more, as by the Scripture is evident. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15.16.17.</note> And as the children of God are led by the Spirit of God, ſo therein they are in the liberty given and allowed of God,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5.6.7.8.</note> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17.18. To ſerve and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him in the glorious miniſtration of the ſpirit, which exceeds and excels that of <hi>Moſes</hi> in a far greater glory, and therein they ought to continue, and not be forced from it by men.</p>
            <p>And as for the people of God (reproachfully) called Quakers, they have under every government peaceably demeaned themſelves ever ſince they were brought into covenant with God, and have ſuffered for their obedience and faithfulneſſe to the Lord, more then any people in this Nation for many years by paſt: and the Lord hath hitherto tryed them, and they have been found faithful to the Lord upon tryal, and they have been tryed by men, and by the power and authority of the kingdome, and do appear upon every tryal to be a people true to their principles to God-ward; and honeſt and upright in their dealings with men, &amp; it is well known to the Nation, that they are a harmleſſe people, and very induſturous and profitable to men, and of an honeſt and good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, unwilling to be burthen ſome unto them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is no juſt cauſe why they ſhould be injured, wronged, or deſtroyed, either in their principles, perſons
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40909:4"/>or eſtates for their tender conſciences and faithfulneſſe to God in matters of Faith and Religion, but ought to be defended and preſerved therein.</p>
            <p>And as for their meetings upon the account of religion to wait upon God as his people, there is as much and more of the ſpirit and life of truth, and of the refreſhing vertue of the word and power of God amongſt them made known from the Lord unto them, for their ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and ſouls conſolation, as amongſt any profeſſing people in the Nation. And it doth appear after ſeveral years trial had of that people, that their meetings never produced any bad effects either to the terrour of the people, or endangering the peace and ſafety of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And therefore they ought not to be ſuppreſſed and broken, but rather countenanced and preſerved in their principles and practiſes, which are ſo faithful and honeſt both towards God and man.</p>
            <p>And whereas it hath been ſaid by ſome of them in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that the Quakers are in ſome part of their princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples much like unto the primitive Chriſtians, who would not take up arms to fight either for or againſt the beſt of Kings or worſt of Tyrants. And therefore the Quakers ſay they are to be commended in that, and others of the Magiſtrates have ſaid as concerning the Quakers having any hand in plotting or deſigning miſchief againſt the King and his government, they are ſo innocent and harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe that they durſt put them into the Magazin, ſo that me thinks they ſhould have no cauſe to ſuſpect them, for indeed they are a people that wiſhes no man any harm, but would rather do good unto all men; therefore they ought not to be deſtroyed or baniſhed, but countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and preſerved in their principles and practiſes which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40909:5"/>are good and anſwers to the witneſſe of God in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of men.</p>
            <p>It is more conſiſtent with trueth, and well pleaſing to God, and agreeable to the other part of the principles of the people of God and primitive Chriſtians,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.10.11.12.14.</note> to ſuffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution for their faithfulneſſe to God, and their continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation in the trueth of the Goſpel, and meeting together to wait upon God, in the way of his worſhip, and have the love and favour of God, then to be unfaithful to God, and untrue to their principles: by forſaking the ſame, for fear of the frownes and rebukes of the ſpirit of the world, or an outward ſuffering from men, and incurre the Anger and diſpleaſure of God for ſo doing, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.26. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.24.25.26.27.28.29.30.31.</p>
            <p>God had a people in <hi>Egypt</hi> under great bondage,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.1.2. <hi>to the</hi> 13.</note> and in great captivity, bowed down and oppreſſed, but he remembred them in his mercy: and ſent his ſervant <hi>Moſes</hi> as his meſſenger to acquaint them with it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 8.1. <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.1.</note> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to ſpeak to <hi>Pharoah</hi> then King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> by whoſe power they were oppreſſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.1.2.3.4.</note> to require of him their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and freedome in the worſhip which God made known and required to be performed and done. But King <hi>Pharoah</hi> denyed the Lord in that thing,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 8.8.12.13.14.15.</note> and gave the Lord an occaſion againſt him, who brought great judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon his kingdome, becauſe he refuſed to give liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the people of God in the worſhip or ſervice of God, and ſaid they were idle,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 8.8 12.13.14.15.</note> and yet when he was under the ſenſe of the judgements of God, he promiſed them liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but he did not regard to make good his promiſe, which ſignified nothing but as a teſtimony againſt him, and to provoke the Lord to wrath,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 8.25.26.27.</note> who renewed his judgements, and weakned the power and policy of <hi>Egypt,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:40909:5"/>for withſtanding the liberty which God required of <hi>Pharoah,</hi> on the behalf of the oppreſſed Iſrael:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.29.30.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.32.33.</note> and in his own time made <hi>Pharoah</hi> to know that he was too ſtrong for him, and by his power alone wrought their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance after many trials, that they might give glory unto him, as by the Scripture is plain, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.40.41.42.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>Pharoah</hi> the King,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.15.16.17. <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.20.21.</note> commanded the Hebrew Midwives to deſtroy all the male children of the Hebrews, when they did the office of a Midwife, yet becauſe the fear of God was in their hearts, they durſt not do it: ſo that they rather chuſed to obey God in preſerving the lives of the innocents, then to obey the command of the King, which was ſo contrary to the minde of the Lord, who would have had the ſeed deſtroyed, which the Lord preſerved and bleſſed.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Pharoah</hi> could have been content to have letten the old ſtock of Iſrael have lived,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.8.9.10.11.12.13.14. &amp;c.</note> if there had been no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, but policy taught him to put a ſtop to that, and if the Lord had not put a ſtop to that deſign, Iſrael had been cut off and deſtroyed in the ſeed.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.17.</note> For if the Hebrew Midwives had not feared and obeyed God rather then man, the male children had been deſtroyed, when they had come out of the womb.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Daniel</hi> was a man beloved and bleſſed of the Lord, and there were ſuch as ſought an occaſion againſt him, with an intent and purpoſe (under the colour of tranſgreſſing a known Law) to have cut him off and deſtroyed him: as there have been and are now ſuch as ſeeks an occaſion againſt the <hi>Daniels</hi> and beloved people of God, with an intent to deſtroy them. And as they could finde no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion againſt <hi>Daniel</hi> but for the law and worſhip of his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40909:6"/>God, ſo they can find no occaſion againſt the <hi>Daniels,</hi> or beloved people of God now, but for their obedience to the law and worſhip of their God, according to the manifeſtation and perſwaſion of the ſpirit and word of God.</p>
            <p>And when they wanted a Law to deſtroy <hi>Daniel</hi> by for his worſhip of God, then all the Preſidents of the Kingdome, the Governours, and the Princes, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours, and the Captaines Aſſembled together to the King,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.4.5.6.7.8.9.</note> and conſulted together to eſtabliſh a Royal Statute, and to make a firm decree, and the King ſigned the ſame, (againſt liberty of conſcience, in matters of faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion) to bind the conſcience, and force it from the worſhip of God for a certain time under pain of death, or by being caſt into the Lions den, as by the Scripture is plain.</p>
            <p>Now when <hi>Daniel</hi> knew that the law was made (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt liberty of conſcience in point of religion and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God) or the writing as aforeſaid was ſealed;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.10.</note> he was faithful to God, in diſobeying ſuch a Statute law againſt liberty of conſcience, rather then diſobey God, and offend his tender conſcience, as by the Scripture appeareth. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.5.6.7.8.9.10.11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And God did own and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance <hi>Daniel</hi> in that thing by preſerving of him, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as innocency was found in <hi>Daniel</hi> before the Lord in ſo doing, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.22.</p>
            <p>Whereby it appears and remaines true, that <hi>Daniel</hi> was innocent and juſtified in the ſight of the Lord, for diſobeying the Statute or decree which was made againſt liberty of conſcience in point of religion and worſhip of God. And it is not unwarrantable or without Scripture example, for the people of God to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40909:6"/>God rather then man, in matters of Faith and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when a law is made againſt Liberty of conſcience in point of religion and worſhip of God as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>The Prieſts were grieved at <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> becauſe they taught the people,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 4.1.2.3.4.</note> and after the Prieſts and the Rulers had taken knowledge of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> that they had been with Ieſus, they was unwilling that the truth ſhould ſpread any further, and to the intent that the truth might be ſuppreſſed and ſpread no further.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 4.15.16.17.</note> Firſt, they conſulted together, and ſaid, let us ſtraitly threaten them that they henceforth ſpeak to no man in this name, as if <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> had been afraid of threatning to have left their Miniſtry like the Prieſts of this time.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 4.18.</note> they commanded them not to ſpeak at all nor teach in the name of Ieſus (for the Prieſts would have none to be teachers but themſelves, and whom they appoint) but <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> anſwered and ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 4.19.20.21.23.</note> whether it be right in the ſight of God to hearken unto you more then unto God, judge yee, for we cannot but ſpeak the things which we have ſeen and heard, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Whereby it is evident and remaines true that the people of God are to obey God, in matters of faith and ſalvation, though they be threatned and commanded to the contrary by men, and it is right in the ſight of God to obey God in ſuch caſes rather then the commands of men, that are contrary to the mind of the Lord, and it would be wrong to diſobey God becauſe of the threats of men as aforeſaid, and it was the principle and practice of the primitive Chriſtians ſo to do, and rather ſuffer by Prieſts, Rulers and Magiſtrates for their obedience and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to God in matters of faith and ſalvation, then to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny their teſtimony, and comply with the ſins of the times,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40909:7"/>for any by ends, and to avoid a ſuffering condition.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Primitive Christians both Ministers and People.</head>
               <p>The Miniſters of the goſpel in the primitive times, were called in queſtion about their doctrine and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry by the Prieſts, Rulers and Magiſtrates, and threatned and commanded to preach no more in the name of Jeſus,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 21.13. to the end <hi>Act.</hi> 22. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.</note> which was indirect oppoſition to liberty of conſcience granted and given by the Lord unto his Miniſters in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of faith and ſalvation, but obſtructed and denyed by Prieſts, Rulers and Magiſtrates then, who commanded them contrary to the commands of God in ſuch caſes, but the Miniſters of the goſpel in the primitive times could not be ſubject to ſuch commands of men, as would have forc't conſcience from performing its duty and ſervice to God in matters of faith and ſalvation, and they ſaid in plain terms without any evaſions, we cannot but ſpeak the things which we have ſeen and heard,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 4.18.19.20.</note> it was matter of conſcience to them, and they would rather ſuffer by men then diſobey God and offend a good conſcience to God-wards as aforeſaid, as by the Scripture is evident and plain.</p>
               <p>The Miniſters of the goſpel and primitive Chriſtians, was no perſecutors, but were perſecuted, for ſaid <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothie</hi> thou haſt fully known my doctrine, manner of life, faith, long ſuffering, charity, patience, perſecutions, afflictions, which came unto me at <hi>Antioch,</hi> at <hi>Iconium,</hi> at <hi>Lyſtra,</hi> what perſecutions I endured, but out of them all the Lord delivered me, yea and all that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus ſhall ſuffer perſecution 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. But evil and ſeducers ſhall wax worſe and worſe,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3 10.11.12.</note> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.13.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40909:7"/>So it appeares and is plain by the Scriptures, that the godly were and are attended with perſecutions, both Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and people, and that by reaſon of evill men and ſeducers, which are and were perſecutors.</p>
               <p>The Miniſters of the goſpel in the primitive times were to continue in the things, which they had learned of God, and were aſſured of as by the Scripture appeareth 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.14. So were the Primitive Chriſtians to continue in the word and doctrine of Chriſt, by which it might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that they were diſciples indeed and lovers of Ieſus.</p>
               <p>And ſaid the Apoſtle ſtand faſt in one ſpirit with one minde, ſtriving together for the faith of the goſpel, and in nothing terrified by your adverſaries, which is to them an evident token of perdition, but to you of Salvation, and that of God , for unto you it is given on the behalf of Chriſt, not only to believe on him, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake. <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.27.28.29.</p>
               <p>Whereby it is evident and remaines true, that the true Chriſtians are not perſecutors, but are true believers in Chriſt, and ſubjects unto him, and a ſuffering condition is anexed to believing, and as none can truly believe unto ſalvation, but them to whom it is given, ſo none can truly ſuffer for Chriſt and the Goſpel, but them to whom it is given and therefore they need not to be terrified by their adverſaries, for it is to the perſecutors an evident token of perdition, but to the true believers in Chriſt who are the true ſufferers it is to the man evident token of ſalvation and that of God as by the Scripture is plain as aforeſaid.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.27.28.29.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Miniſters of the Goſpel of Chriſt who have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived their miniſtry of God, to miniſter from him to the ſoules of the people, are in preaching the word to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, according to the charge
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40909:8"/>given before the Lord, as by the Scripture is plain. And when is preaching the word out of ſeaſon, but when it is either forbidden by men,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.2.3.4.</note> or when they will not endure ſound doctrine, but after their own luſts ſhall heap up to themſelves teachers having itching ears, as by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture appears.</p>
               <p>The Scriptures declare that the time will come, when people will not endure ſound doctrine, but after their own luſts ſhall heap up to themſelves Teachers, having itching ears, and they ſhall turn away their ears from the truth, and ſhall be turned unto fables, and if that time be already come, (or be yet to come) at ſuch a time, the Miniſters of the goſpel of Chriſt who have received their miniſtry of God, are not to change their religion, and turn away from the truth and worſhip of God, (like the Prieſts of this Prieſt turning time,) but the miniſters of the goſpel, are to watch in all things, and endure afflictions, do the work of Evangeliſts, and make full proof of their miniſtry as it appeareth 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.2.3.4.5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the godly meetings of the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and Saints in Chriſt Jeſus, and people of God in former Ages.</head>
               <p>We do not read in the Scriptures of truth that the people of God and true Chriſtians did ever impriſon, fine, and baniſh, or ſell one another for their religion and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: but we read that <hi>Haman</hi> did envie the good and welfare of the Jewes, and ſaid unto the King, there is a certain people ſcattered abroad, and diſperſed among the people in all the provinces of thy Kingdome, and their lawes are divers from all people, neither keep they the Kings lawes, therefore it is not for the Kings profit to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40909:8"/>ſuffer them, if it pleaſe the King let it be written that they may be deſtroyed, and I will pay ten thouſand talents of Silver to the hands of thoſe that have the charge of the buſineſſe, to bring it into the Kings treaſuries, and the King conſented unto him, and they were deſigned for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction as by the Scripture is plain, <hi>Eſter,</hi> 3.8.9.10.11.12.13.14.15.</p>
               <p>But it pleaſed the Lord to let the King know the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of his people, and how they were not ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous unto the welfare and ſafety of his Kingdome, as <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> had informed him, and the King changed his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, revoked what he had ſigned againſt them, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came under God a preſerver of them, and the King de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared and ſaid, oftentimes fair ſpeeches of thoſe that are put in truſt to manage their friends affairs, hath cauſed many that are in authority to be pertakers of innocent blood, and hath enwrapped them in remedileſſe calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, beguiling with the falſhood and deceipt of their lew'd diſpoſition, the Innocency &amp; goodneſſe of Princes: now ye may ſee this, as we have declared, not ſo much by antient Hiſtories, as yee may, if yee ſearch what hath been wickedly don of late, through the peſtilent behaviour of them that are unworthily placed in authority, and we muſt take care for the time to come, that our kingdome may be quiet and peaceable for all men, both by chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our purpoſes, and alwayes judging things that are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident with more equal proceeding,<note place="margin">See it in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crypha.</note> as appeareth in the letter of <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> wherein he taxeth <hi>Haman</hi> and revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the decree procured by <hi>Haman</hi> to deſtroy the Jewes, <hi>Ester.</hi> 16 Chapter,</p>
               <p>Would it not be good in the ſight of God, and very profitable to this Kingdome, and commendable alſo, if
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40909:9"/>the King and the Parliament did under God take ſuch a care for the time to come, as that the Kingdome might be quiet and peaceable for all men, both by repealing that law made againſt liberty of conſcience, and allowing an equal liberty to all men, in the exerciſe of their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences as to God-wards in matters of faith and ſalvation: and alwaies by judging things that are evident with more equal proceeding,</p>
               <p>There was a time in the dayes of the Prophet <hi>Malachi,</hi> wherein the words of ſome were ſtout againſt the Lord,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 3, 13.</note> yet they would have excuſed themſelves, ſaying, what have we ſpoken ſo much againſt the Lord? to the which the Lord anſwered them by his Prophet ſaying, Ye have ſaid it is in vain to ſerve God, and what profit is it that we have kept his Ordinance,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.14.</note> and that we have walked mournfully before the Lord, and they called the proud happy,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.15.</note> and they that wrought wickedneſſe were ſet up, and they that tempted God were delivered.</p>
               <p>Then they that feared the Lord ſeparated from the Iniquities of the time, met often together and ſpoke one to another, and the Lord was preſent in their aſſemblies after a ſpiritual manner,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16.</note> and did own them and their meetings, for he both hearkned and heard them, and a book of remembrance was written before the Lord, for them that feared him, and thought upon his name, and the Lord made promiſe to ſuch for their encouragement and comfort:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17.</note> and they ſhall be mine ſaith the Lord in that day when I make up my jewels, and I will ſpare them (that ſerveth me) as a man ſpareth his ſan that ſerveth him, then ſhall ye return and diſcern between the Righteous and the Wicked, between him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16.17.18.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:40909:9"/>When Chriſt Jeſus was come in the dayes of his humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation and were converſant amongſt men, after that <hi>John</hi> was caſt into priſon, for preaching and performing the Office and duty of a Miniſter,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 4.12.13.14.15.16.17.</note> or delivering that meſſage which he was ſent about from the Lord to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, as a foreruuner of Chriſt, then Chriſt Ieſus him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf began to preach, and ſay, <hi>Repent for the kingdome of Heaven is at hand, and there followed him great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of people from</hi> Galilee, <hi>and from</hi> Dicapolis,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.25.</note> 
                  <hi>and from</hi> Judea, <hi>and from</hi> Hieruſalem, <hi>and from beyond</hi> Jordan, <hi>and ſeeing the multitude, he went up into a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and when he was ſet, he opened his mouth and taught them,</hi> as you may read, <hi>Mat</hi> 5.1.2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if there had been a law made againſt meeting to the number of five or above, (and not in Pariſh Churches or Chappels, and contrary to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon way of meeting, preaching and hearing, under pain of Impriſonment, Fines, and Baniſhment,) then Chriſt and the multitude muſt either not have met af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that manner, or elſe they might have ſuffered as his Saints and ſervants are like to do now, but it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by the example of Chriſt, that he never intended any ſuch law to be made in ſuch direct oppoſition to his example and practice, and though the people came from many places, and parts of the Country to that meeting with Jeſus upon the mountain, there was no danger to the ſafery and happineſſe of the government, though ſuſpition might ariſe in the minds of ſome, and be ready to judge it unſafe to ſuffer ſuch meetings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And it came to paſſe that when Jeſus had finiſhed theſe ſayings, he departed from</hi> Galilee,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>and came into the coaſts of</hi> Judea, <hi>beyond</hi> Jordan, <hi>and great multitudes followed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40909:10"/>him,</hi> as by the Scripture is plain, But if Chriſt was here now and did ſo, he muſt be impriſoned, and baniſhed by a law, and by that law the people might be kept from following Chriſt, or elſe ſuffer impriſonment and baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for following of him, and that by ſuch as pretends to be friends unto him. But it is not every one that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends love to him, or ſaith Lord Lord, <hi>that ſhall enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kingdome of Heaven, but he that doth the will of the Father,</hi> as Chriſt Ieſus hath declared and ſaid.</p>
               <p>And Jeſus came at another time nigh unto the Sea of <hi>Galilee,</hi> and went up into a mountain, and ſate down and great multitudes came unto him,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.29.30.</note> as by the Scripture is plain, whereby it is evident and remaines true, that there either was no law that prohibited ſuch great meetings on mountaines, and to keep the people back from following of Ieſus, after that manner, or if there were any ſuch lawes then in being, they were not regarded by Chriſt, and the followers of him, in matters of faith and ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>And at another time Ieſus entred into <hi>Capernaum,</hi> and it was noiſed that he was in the houſe, and ſtraitway ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were gathered together, inſomuch that there was no room to receive them, no not ſo much as about the door, and he preached the word unto them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark</hi> 2.1.2.</note> as you may read in the Scripture of truth. But if Ieſus was here now and did ſo, might not he and the people be impriſoned and bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed or ſold for ſo doing, conſider well of it, and let the Lord judge in this caſe.</p>
               <p>And before Chriſts aſcention, being aſſembled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his diſciples and friends which were about the number of five, he commanded them that they ſhould not depart from Ieruſalem, but wait for the promiſe of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40909:10"/>the Father, which ſaith he, ye have heard of me, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.1.2.3.4. <hi>And when they were come in, they went up into an upper room, where abode both</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> Iames, <hi>and</hi> Iohn, <hi>and</hi> Andrew, Philip, <hi>and</hi> Thomas, Bartholomew, <hi>and</hi> Matthew, Iames <hi>the ſon of</hi> Alpheus, <hi>and</hi> Simon Zelotes, <hi>and</hi> Iudas <hi>the brother of</hi> Iames, (which were above the number of five) and they did not diſperſe themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to numbers under five, but theſe all continued with one accord in prayer and ſupplication with the women, and <hi>Mary</hi> the mother of Ieſus, and with his brethren as you may read <hi>Act.</hi> 1.13.14.</p>
               <p>And if there had been ſuch a law that they might not have met upon the account of religion (from a pariſh Church) to the number of five or above under pain of impriſonment and baniſhment, as now,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 1.3.4. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.13.14.</note> they might either have diſobeyed the commands of Chriſt, or elſe have broken ſuch a law, as is directly againſt that command of the Lord Ieſus, as by the Scripture is evident.</p>
               <p>And when the day of Penticoſt was fully come, they were all with one accord in one place, (and not diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into companies under the number of five) as you may read <hi>Act.</hi> 2.1. And ſuddenly there came a ſound from Heaven, as of a ruſhing mighty winde, and it fill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the houſe where they were ſitting, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 2. (ſo that they were not met in a pariſh Church or Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel) but in a houſe, and God mightily honoured their meeting, for they were filled with the Holy Ghoſt, and began to ſpeak as the ſpirit gave them utterance, as by the Scripture is evident. <hi>Ast.</hi> 2.1.2.3.4.</p>
               <p>And the Servants of Ieſus did meet together in houſes and in great numbers alſo, or elſe how ſhould there have been three thouſand ſoules added unto them on one day,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40909:11"/>as there was by the preaching of <hi>Peter, Act.</hi> 2. And in private houſes they met often, and alſo in multitudes, as by the Scripture appeareth, and ſome of them believed and conſorted with <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 17.4.5.6.7.8.</note> and of the devout Greeks a great multitude, and of the chief women not a few, but the Iewes which believed not moved with envie, took unto them certain lew'd fellowes of the baſer ſort and gathered a company, and let all the City on an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roar, and aſſaulted the houſe of <hi>Jaſon,</hi> and ſought to bring them out to the people, and they drew <hi>Jaſon</hi> and certain of the brethren unto the Rulers of the city, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe that have turned the world upſide down are come hither alſo, whom <hi>Iaſon</hi> hath received, ſaying, that there is another King, one Ieſus, and they troubled the people and the Rulers of the city, when they heard theſe things, ſo you may ſee how the old envious profeſſours, and the baſer ſort of people, did trouble the people and Rulers by haling out and abuſing the primitive chriſtians and reporting of them as aforeſaid, but the true chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans did not perſecute any but were perſecuted, as by the Scripture appeareth. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.4.5.6.7.8,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And after the uproar was ceaſed, Paul called unto him the Diſciples, and embraced them, and departed for to go into Macedonia, Acts</hi> 20.1. <hi>And upon the first day of the week the Diſciples came together, and met</hi> neither in a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Church nor a Chappel,<note place="margin">Act. 20.8.</note> but <hi>in a private houſe, and Paul continued his Speech until midnight in the Chamber where they were gathered together;</hi> Acts 20.7, 8.</p>
               <p>Whereby it is evident and remains true, that it was the practice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles to meet together in private houſes, and in great numbers, and they never made any uproar, nor abuſed any, but they were abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40909:11"/>and ſuffered, as thoſe do who follow their examples,<note place="margin">Eph. 5. Gal. 5.16.22, 23, 24, 25. Heb. 10.22, 23.</note> and live in the Spirit as they did. It was the practiſe of the primitive Chriſtians to aſſemble themſelves together, and wait upon God in the way of his Worſhip, and they were to hold faſt their Profeſſion without wavering, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was faithful that promiſed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. though they were perſecuted for meeting and worſhipping contrary to the cuſtome of the envious Jewes, and contrary to the way and worſhip of the World, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Whereby it is evident and remains true, that it is the duty of true Chriſtians, Saints, and Believers in Chriſt Jeſus, to be true and faithful unto God, in meeting to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the Way and Worſhip of God, and mind their continuation with God in the ſame, though they be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with a ſuffering condition from men for ſo doing: and as it is their duty to meet together as the Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of God, according to the manifeſtation and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of God, ſo it is a danger to neglect the ſame, as by the Scripture is evident and plain, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22, 23.24,25.</p>
               <p>And as Preaching is not an Art of Nature, but a ſpritual gift, ſo none are required by the Lord to miniſter from him to the people, but them to whom it is given, and all have a true right given and allowed of God, to miniſter from him to the people, to whom that gift of Miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is given, and ſuch ought not to be forbidden,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.10, 11.</note> becauſe there is a toleration to ſuch given and granted in heaven, as every man hath received the gift, ſo let him miniſter the ſame one to another, as good Stewards of the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold grace of God; If any man ſpeak, let him ſpeak as the Oracles (or Sayings) of God: If any man Miniſter, let him do it as of the Ability which God giveth, that God in all things may be glorified, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is written 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10, 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:40909:12"/>
                  <note place="margin">Order of Baptiſme.</note> And for as much as it is a Fundamental of the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal or Proteſtant Religion, and according to the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions and Canons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that all who are Admitted into Church fellowſhip, muſt in order to their Admiſſion, and in order to the obtaining to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the honourable Title of Chriſtians, promiſe and vow unto God before many witneſſes, to forſake the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and all his Works, and to keep Gods holy Will and Commandments, and walk in the ſame all the days of their lives: Are not the Proteſtants or Epiſcopals hereby bound from perſecuting any for Conſcience towards God, in matters of Faith and Salvation? Becauſe it is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be a work of the Devil, and contrary to the will of God to perſecute Chriſtians for matters of Faith and Salvation in point of Religion and Worſhip of God.</p>
               <p>And for as much as it is declared in the Common Prayer Book or Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Coll. for Peace.</note> that the Service of God is perfect freedom, whether ought any to be forced either to it or from it by outward compulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but rather left to their freedome, that God may convince and perſwade them? Becauſe whatſoever is not of Faith is ſin, and every man ought to be fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his own heart, in matters of Faith and Salvation, and it properly belongs to ſhe Lord to make known his own Worſhip, who knows how to perſwade the heart both to believe, and cloſe in with the ſame.</p>
               <p>And whereas it is ſaid in the Common Prayer, that God is the Author of Peace, and Lover of Concord, ought not the Epiſcopals or Proteſtants to be like minded unto him? If ſo, they would ſee it to be below the life and ſpirit of a true Chriſtian, to force Conſcience before they convince it: And ſo ought to ſeek their peace and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40909:12"/>and not their deſtruction and Ruine, who are yet unconvinced or perſwaded by them, who themſelves do not walk up to their profeſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Com. up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Feaſts of Trin.</note> And whereas in the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England</hi> it is acknowledged that it is very meet, right, and our bounden duty, that we ſhould at all times, and in all places, (worſhip and ſerve the Lord) or give Thanks un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Almighty and Everlaſting God, why then ſhould we be bound from doing that which is accounted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be very meet, right, and our bounden duty at any time, and in any place, eſpecially by them who do own and profeſs the ſame as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>And whereas the Prieſts, Biſhops, and Curates do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and confeſs by the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that there is no health in them, meaning no ſouls health, nor ſaving health in any of them, becauſe it is generally acknowledged by them, and upon a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Account, what Reaſon can be produced in Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why any man ſhould be forced againſt his Conſcience to come to ſeek Cure of them, who plainly ſay they have no health in them; and if they have no health in them, as they ſay they have not, Have they any Cure of Souls in them? If not, to whom muſt the wounded ſouls go to be cured? Is it not beſt to leave them to their freedome, that the Lord may direct them to whom to go to be cured, when they are wounded by ſin, and the Temptations of Satan, that they may alſo be delivered from under the bondage of Corruption.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:40909:13"/>
               <head>Concerning the Church according to the Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Canons, or Liturgie; And al o of practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing according to the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. AS to the Church, who are accounted true Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof, and the Condition of their being admitted into Fellowſhip therewith, according to the Conſtitutions, and Canons, or Liturgie; None are to be Admitted into Church-Fellowſhip, neither can any obtain to themſelves the honourable Title of Chriſtians, but ſuch as do Covenant with God by Promiſe and Vow before many Witneſſes, to be perfect and free from ſin; Firſt, by forſaking the Devil and all his Works: And ſecondly, by keeping Gods holy Will and Commandments, and walking in the ſame all the dayes of their lives. And ſeeing that none can be Admitted into Church-Fellowſhip nor obtain to themſelves that Honourable Title of Chriſtians, but upon the aforeſaid Conditions, Have, and Do not all thereby, who have Entered and are Admitted as aforeſaid, both Covenanted, and do Covenant with God againſt Perſecution about mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion? And if they perſecute any upon that Account, Do they not break Covenant with God, and Violate the Fundamentalls of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:40909:13"/>Secondly, None are accounted Members of the Church, according to the Liturgie, but ſuch as are born again of Water and the Spirit, and are by Regeneration made Members of Chriſt, Children of God, and Inheritors of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven. If it be true that the Prieſts did Regenerate and Inveſt us into a Right to God's Kingdome, by that Act of Baptiſme, ſo called, as they have told us they did, What true Spiritual Power and Goſpel Authority have the Biſhops and Prieſts to diſpoſſeſſe us of that Right to Gods Kingdome again, either by Church Cenſure or Excommunication.</p>
               <p>And if they made us Children of God, Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, and Inheritors of the Kingdome of Heaven, by that Act of Baptiſme, ſo called, as they ſay they did; Then what Spiritual Right and Goſpel Authority have they to perſecute the Members of Chriſt, and Children of God, about matters of Faith and Salvation, and things apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the Kingdome of God? Is not that to act contrary to the Liturgie of the Church? And do not ſuch actions ſtaine their Profeſſion, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olate the Fundamentals of the Epiſcopal and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion?</p>
               <p>And if they made us Children of God, Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, and Inheritors of the Kingdome of Heaven, by that act of Baptiſme, ſo called; Did they but mate us ſo for that preſent time onely, or for continuance and perpetuity? By their own account they did not make us ſo for that preſent
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40909:14"/>time onely, but for continuance and perpetuity; for they ſay they made us Inheritors of the Kingdom of Heaven, and their Faith and Judgement is, that we cannot Inherit the Kingdome of Heaven whilſt in this Life, till after Death; and therefore it muſt needs be underſtood that they intended to make us ſo for continuance and perpetuity: Then what Right have they to Excommunicate and Perſecute us? For if they cut off the Members of Chriſt either by Excommunication or Perſecution, do they not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy Chriſt in his Members in ſo doing? And is not that contrary to the Minde and Will of God, and againſt the Innocency and true Intent of the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England?</hi> And doth not ſuch proceedings beget a diſlike and diſ-eſteem to them who ſo openly and manifeſtly erre from their owne Principles or Fundamentals in matters of Religion and Practiſe as aforeſaid?</p>
               <p>And for as much as the Biſhops and Prieſts doe promiſe to People, that by the Act of Baptiſme (ſo called) they do Regenerate their Children, and do thereby conclude them Regenerate, ſaying Dearly Beloved, Seeing this Childe is Regenerate and Borne again, let us give Thanks; Then if by that Act they do not Regenerate them, they doe neither truly Baptize them, nor Admit them into Church Fellowſhip; Do not they therefore pretend to do that which they neither intend, or really do not perform? And is it not time for people to take notice of them? For if no Prieſt in <hi>England</hi> can Regenerate any, then no Prieſt in England can
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40909:14"/>Baptize any, who promiſe and pretend to Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them by that Act, as aforeſaid, and do not.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing that by the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the Church is declared to be the Houſhold and Family of God; and by the Act that none may meet out of their owne Family, above the number of five, under pretence of Religion, and Worſhip of God, contrary to the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> Then it ſeems that they who are of that Family, and the whole Houſhold and Family of God may meet together by that Act, and not above five amongſt them that are not of the Houſhold and Family of God.</p>
               <p>And the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth plainly ſay, that the whole Body of the Church is governed and ſanctified by the Spirit of God: So that the Houſhold and Family of God are under the Teachings, Sanctification, and Government of the Spirit of God: And by the Act it ſeemes all ſuch may meet together to Worſhip God; and not above five joyn with them, that are not Governed and Sanctified by the Spirit of God; for they are not Members of the Church, nor of the Houſhold and Family of God, who are not Governed and Sanctified by the Spirit of God: becauſe the whole Body of the Church is ſaid to be Governed and Sanctified by the Spirit of God, and that according to the Liturgie, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Is it not evident then, or may it not be concluded that by the ſaid Act there is a toleration given, for all to meet together, who are under the adminiſtration,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40909:15"/>and teachings of God, who are governed and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the ſpirit of God, and then what will this be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the meeting of the Quakers, and innocent people of God, if rightly underſtood, and not perverted, becauſe they are the onely people that meet together in point of religion and worſhip of God, according to the Liturgie, becauſe they are under the adminiſtrations, and teachings of God, and are governed and ſanctified by the ſpirit of God.</p>
               <p>And doth it not remain true, that thoſe who are prohibited by the act to meet above the number of five, contrary to the Liturgie of the Church of England, under pretence of religion, are ſuch as are not of the houſhold and family of God, that is to ſay ſuch as daily errs and goes aſtray from the wayes of God, and are not governed and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the ſpirit of God as aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Infants Baptiſme.</head>
               <p>And as concerning Baptiſme, if the thing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by promiſed and pretended be not effected, the end doth not anſwer the means as they call it, or indeed the meanes doth not lead to the end, ſo that it is more a pretence and ſhew or ſhadow then any thing of ſubſtance, and as neceſſary unto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and when the means leads to the end, or the end anſwers the means, ſo that the Prieſts do make it appear that they really can, and do regenerate people by that act of baptiſme ſo called,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40909:15"/>as they pretend, then we ſhall be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> them, and bring children unto them, to have that conferred upon them, and in the mean time it is but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to be excuſed for not bringing little child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren unto them, whilſt that part is more pretence then real practice or ſubſtance, and we judge it a reaſonable thing to be freed, and clearly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted from all Eccleſiaſtical cenſures, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall puniſhments concerning the ſame, and if you think otherwiſe, let the Lord and all true ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced, ſound, upright hearted Chriſtians judge between you and us in this caſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Sacrament ſo called.</head>
               <p>Is there any true ſpirituall right or goſpel autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity whereby any ſhould be puniſhed by Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal cenſures or temporal puniſhments for not receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that as an Ordinance of Chriſt, which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures no where makes mention off? if you ſay no;</p>
               <p>Then we ſay the Scripture nowhere makes mention of the word Sacrament, in any place that we ever read of, and if you can produce any place of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that plainly makes mention of the word Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, when you have produced that Scripture, we ſhall take it into due conſideration, and if you ſay there is no ſuch Scripture to be produced, but the word ſacrament is a ſignificant word, and it ſignifies the receiving of Chriſt Ieſus, and of an inward and ſpiritual grace which are holy things if ſo? then to receive Chriſt Ieſus in ſpirit and the grace of God is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40909:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>to receive the ſignification of the word Sacrament, and ſo effectually to receive the Sacrament or the thing ſignified, which is the end of the ſign, and we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and do receive Chriſt Ieſus, and the inward grace of the ſpirit of God, and ſo in effect do receive the Sacrament, or ſignification of the ſign, and ought to be freed from all Eccleſiaſtical cenſures, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral puniſhments concerning the ſame.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Then to meet together in point of Religion and worſhip of God with them that are governed and ſanctified by the ſpirit of God, is to come to the Church, and that according to the Liturgie or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer book, therefore ſuch are to be tolerated, and ought not to be moleſted or troubled, but rather freed from all Eccleſiaſtical cenſures and temporal pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments concerning the ſame.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To meet together to preach and pray, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form duty to God in point of Religion and worſhip of God, is not to meet contrary to the practice of the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of the Church of England, becauſe they pretend to do the ſame, therefore they who meet together in the fear, wiſdome, and ſpirit of God, to preach, pray, and perform duty to God, in point of Religion, as worſhippers of him, ought not to be moleſted, diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or called in queſtion for ſo doing.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
